Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 3 -- Letters to Franklin 1778 April-December Mss.B.F85inventory03
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 July 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Conway, ------. Paris
    Concerning the weight and price of two brass cannon and where they are to be seen. Wishes to known if there is any recent news from America, especially if there are any tidings of his son [General Thomas Conway].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 July 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Lutterloh, Major Henry Emanuel. Brunswick
    Begging Franklin to send the enclosed to his brother and permit the answer to be addressed to his care.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 July 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Reine, D.E. Versailles
    Mr. Willing despatched by Congress with a ship and thirty men to raid the left bank of the Mississippi; damage he inflicted.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 July 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Guichard,-----, ainé. Marennes
    Claims a certain sum due his brother, Augustin Guichard, now in prison, who was officer on board the Lexington for a year and whose salary for that time and his share of the prizes are still due him; mentions various people who will endorse his brother's application.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 July 26; A.L.S. 4p. L. 4p.; Genet, [Edme Jacques]
    Sorry No. 49 appeared before he received Dr. Cooper's letter; it shall be published in No. 50 [Affaires d'Angleterre] with an account of the arrival of the Duchesse de Grammont. The intention of two printers to establish a Gazette in Boston composed principally of articles from France, likely to promote the union and welfare of both countries; suggests a similar enterprise of which he desires to be the head; sketches his ideas on this point.
    P. S. Question of the probability of a large sale of these papers in America.
    (In English.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 July 26; A.L.S. 3p.; Valltravers, Rodolph. Bienne
    Ignorant of the fate of his last two letters. Sends by M. de Gruffly, the bearer, a sketch of a few principles wheron to build a lasting foundation of friendship between the thirteen republican states of America and of Switzerland; if Franklin approves it, desires that it may be conveyed to Congress, after submitting it to the Minister of His Most Christian Majesty and through his ambassador, to the several cantons; offers his services in case of a similar alliance between the United States and the naval republics of Venice and Genoa; begs for the promised copy of the treaty with France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 July 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    Declines the invitation on the plea that his affairs do not permit him to quit Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 July 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Berny, Chevalier de
    Five months have elapsed since he took the liberty of dedicating and sending to Franklin a pamphlet entitled "L' oeil de Maritre ou Essaisur le Ministère"; this work was kindly received by le Comte de Vergennes to whom his services and talents are known; begs Franklin to acknowledge its receipt.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 July 27; A.L.S. 3p.; Simpson, Thomas. Brest
    Has received his appoinmnent and taken command of the Ranger; disposition to be made of his prisoners; the prizes not yet sold.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 July 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Moreau, Nicolas. Cadiz
    Since the treaty between the United States and France, supposed that all merchandise loaded in England on French ships would be safe; this was not the case with the ship Fortune on her passage from London to Cadiz; she was taken by the Americans and carried to Boston; the cargo was owned by him and he begs Franklin to aid him in recovering its value.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 July 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Iselin, Isaac. Basel
    Has been engaged for years on a periodical publication destined to enlighten his fellow-citizens on the needs and rights of humanity; believes there is a germ of perfection in mankind that can be developed by cultivation; for this purpose desires to know those facts which are worthy of imitation; America can furnish a great number of these; begs Franklin to point out to him at Philadelphia or elsewhere, a correspondent who will furnish him, from time to time, with papers of this kind.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 July 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Ayres, John. Bordeaux
    Announcing his arrival from Boston with a packet for their Excellencies; unable to deliver it himself owing to illness, so sends it by a trust-worthy hand. Has a commission as captain in the Continental navy if his services are desired.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 July 29; A.L.S. 2p. and Diss. 15p.; Pelletier, -----. Paris
    Enclosing a plan for founding alms houses or state institutions for the indigent and homeless.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 July 30; L.S. 1p.; Holker, Jean. Rouen
    At M. Lalanne's request, recommends the bearer, M. le Baron de Reuschenberg to Franklin's kind notice.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 July 30; L. 8p.; Sieulanne, -----. Santa Cruz de Teneriffe
    Copies of his letters to and from M. Cologan and to Franklin, concerning the arrest of his vessel by order of the Governor of the Canaries; this vessel was the English brigantine, the Countess of Moreton, which he was conducting to Martinique by order of Captain Cunningham; reasons given for the detention of this vessel; desires Franklin to use his influence with the Court of Spain to obtain indemnity for his enforced delay and satisfaction for the insults offered to Captain Cunningham and to the flag.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 July 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Hancock, Philip. Amsterdam
    Has come to Paris to inform him of past proceedings and to procure instructions for the future; has information to impart that was judged imprudent to be sent by letter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 July 31; L.S. 2p.; Whipple, Abraham. Paimboeuf
    Reasons for his delay in sailing; acknowledging Franklin's favors of the 13th and 16th insts.; has written Captain Tucker to join him with the Boston and to Captain Simpson to fit the Ranger for sea with all possible despatch. His cargo and provisions on board and his men in good health and high spirits; hopes to pay his respects to the Guernsey and Jersey privateers.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 July 31; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Quoting extracts from ministerial despatches. Frequent desertions in the Dutch army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 July; A.L.S. 2p.; Ogden, Titus. L'Orient
    Account of his former arrival in Nantes and the despatch and economy with which Mr. Moylan repaired and loaded his ship; contrasts him with Mr. Puchelberg, a foreigner, appointed by Mr. Schweighauser, who does not speak English, but knows very well how to charge.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 August 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Moylan, James. L'Orient
    The frigate Boston sailed that morning with her three prizes. Offering to freight certain goods which were left behind by Captain Tucker.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, Jacques.
    Enclosing letters which he begs to have forwarded to M. d'Arcel, at Boston; begs that twelve Louis d'or may be sent to M. Bresson's brother-in-law, now in prison at Okehampton, and also five Louis d'or to his companion in captivity, the writer's nephew, Dubourg de la Blanchardière; counts on Franklin to procure their exchange as soon as possible.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 1; A.L.S. 3p.; Vaughan, Benjamin
    His letter filled him with utmost transports; dares not tell him what he had feared. The leaves Franklin wrote for are sent, directed to M. de Chaumont. Concerning the accounts with Johnson.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 1; L.S. 1p.; Smets, Veuve Jean Martin. Anvers
    A packet has been expressed to him received from Mr. Aychmayer of Rotterdam.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Bussy-Dagoneau, comte de. Enclos du Temple
    His desire to fight the enemies of America; illness and law-suits keep him in France; some day he will arrive in Boston, too late for his own glory, but in time to admire that of America.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 August 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Collas, Peter. Passy
    Empowering the commissioners to act on his behalf with regard to indemnity for his vessel Triton.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 1; L.S. 4p.; Pezerat, -----. Dijon
    Wishes to settle in the United States with his family.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Patrick Clear or Cleary. Lisbon
    His brother, Timothy, resided in Newburn, North Carolina, and on dying, bequeathed a considerable fortune; prevented by illness from going at once to America with full power of attorney; informed of an act whereby the lands and effects of all those who did not appear before a certain time were confiscated; begs Franklin's advice and assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 1; A.L.S. 1p.; O'Gorman, Thomas, chevalier
    Including Franklin's nephew, Mr. Williams, in an invitation for the following Monday.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Grove, Leslie. London
    Writes on behalf of Thomas Truman, a passenger on the Lord Chatham, who was taken prisoner and is now at Brest; has a wife and three little children; begs that Franklin will give orders to set him at liberty.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Ischiffely, -----. Berne
    Wishes to devote his remaining days to the political welfare of society; nothing could better contribute to this end than the diffusion among all peoples of the new constitutions of America; proposes to translate them for his own country, Germany and Italy; finds fault with the partial collection translated by M. Regnier.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, Jacques. Paris
    Concerning the memoir from M. Poissionier, recommending M. Maubaillon for the office of Consul at Calais.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Sowden, Hannah. Rotterdam
    Announcing the death of her father; begs Franklin to communicate the fact to Mr. Gordon.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 August 2; A. Dr. by Benjamin Franklin of L. 1p.; Hancock, Philip?. Paris
    Has assisted many subjects of the United States imprisoned at Plymouth Dock, England, to escape. Came to Paris to confer with the Commissioners and was robbed by a companion. Begs for assistance to return home.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Genet, [Edme Jacques]
    Is hard at work translating the interesting Gazettes of Pennsylvania of May 30th and June 20th; is hourly expecting the English accounts of the battle of the 27th; begs Franklin to send at once certain articles for the affaires d'Angleterre, No. 50.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 3; A.L.S. 4p.; Fyot, -----
    Has long desired to show him certain discoveries, useful to humanity; concerning his own invention of a mechanical pulley, shown at the last meeting of the Society of Emulation; it received the approval of M. Millon; to this discovery he adds that of the trisection of the angle and other mathematical inventions.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Borel, -----. Pierefitte
    The plate engraved according to the design is well-advanced; begs Franklin to give him an to make certain chages.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Clouet, -----. Paris
    Concerning a letter he received from le Sieur Fouquet, Master Gunpowder Maker at Yorktown, Pa., enclosing three bills of exchange on Franklin; desires to know where he can receive the amount; begs Franklin to forward him certain important letters.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 3; A.L.S. 1p.; White, James
    Desires to go to America with his family; begs Franklin to assist him in this project. Has made a most valuable discovery for which England, France and Spain have offered him 10,000 pounds each, but they shall never get it, provided Franklin will aid him to go to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 3; L.S. 3p.; Tessier, ------. Bordeaux
    Proposes to emigrate to the United States with six farmers. Inquires about concession granted to emigrants.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 4; A.L.S. 2p.; de Grandchamp, Person. Senoncourt
    Request for his son to enter the American army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 4; L.S. 2p.; Parsons, William. London
    His journey to Paris with his wife to offer his services to the United States, which were rejected; his friends and family in England turned against him and his money was soon exhausted; returned to London, leaving his wife in Paris, but has been so threatened that he dares not stir out of his room; Chevalier Hickey will inform Franklin of his wife's wretched situation; hopes he will aid her to join him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 4; A.L.S. 2p.; de Goyon, Chevalier Carré, Lisbon
    Recommending M. Boniface, of Lisbon, for the position of consul.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 August 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Bingham, William. St Pierre
    Drawing upon them for a certain sum of money.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Lee, William
    Authorizing him to deliver to Mr. Ross all the papers of the late Mr. Thomas Morris either of a private nature or relating to the house of Messrs. Willing, Morris and Co.; those that relate to public business, Franklin will doubtless continue to keep.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Tristan-Brision, — abbé de.
    Concerning an important letter, addressed to Franklin, which he begs him to send for.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Genet, [Edme Jacques]
    Returns Dr. Cooper's letter together with some English Gazettes just arrived; No. 50 [Affaires d'Angleterre] will appear in two days.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 August 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. Passy
    Terms on which the Ranger's seamen were engaged; advances he made them out of his own pocket; begs Franklin to order receipts to be given him for his indemnification and also for his stores, furniture, etc.; asks also that the men who landed with him at Whitehaven may be recommended to the bounty of Congress.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 August 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Bingham, William. St Pierre
    According to the instructions of Congress, has drawn a bill on them for a certain amount, payable at a given time.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 6; A.L.S. 1p.; de Grandchamp, Person. Senoncourt
    Apologizing for having forgotten his address in his former letter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Stadel, -----. Paris
    Desires him to state what style of knives and forks he wishes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Suavelier, -----. Caen
    Concerning three sailors who claim to be Americans; made prisoners by the English but effected their escape; writes to Franklin at their request to procure them the means of returning to their country.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 August 6; A.L.S. 7p.; Fowler, Alexander. London
    Served in the British army for eighteen years; the harsh treatment he received from Generals Gage and Howe, owing to his well-known sympathy with the Sons of Liberty; returned to England with his wife and brought an action against General Gage for damages; the trial was quashed and a hearing denied him; begs them to procure him and his wife a passage to any part of the United States. Encloses testimonials of his conduct and character, also an extract from an English officer's letter, showing the prejudice held against him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 6; A.L.S. 3p.; Brongniart, Antoine Louis
    The new experiments he has made in electricity have excited quite a sensation among the physicists; invites Franklin to witness certain experiments which he proposes to attempt at his own house.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Niles, Robert. Nantes
    His arrival at Paimboeuf; will proceed at once on his voyage; enclosing a bill for the purchase of type.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 7; A.L.S. 11p.; de Reuschenberg, Baron F.E. Paris
    Having experienced domestic troubles and the loss of a considerable fortune, is determined to expatriate himself; desires to enter the army of the United States, provided he receives the rank of officer. His wish to raise a legion, to be formed according to the ideas of the later Marshal de Saxe; if his services are rejected, desires still to live and die in America, preferably in Pennsylvania, because that Province produced a Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 7; L.S. 1p.; John Atwood, Jacob Vere and Nathan Chadwick
    American prisoners who have escaped to France; appeal for assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 8; A.L.S. 4p.; De St Martin, -----. Versailles
    Request to enter the army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, Jacques.
    Recommends the enclosed memoir to Franklin's notice, although he does not expect a favorable reply, but the sender would have taken it ill if he had refused; begs for at least a few lines he can show the applicant.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Sharp, Granville. Old Jewry
    Recommending Mr. Lawrence Brooke, of Virginia, to Franklin's friendship; the object of his residence in Europe was to pursue his education, but he has not imbibed the least prejudice against his native land; he desires to return to America with his brother, Mr. Robert Brooke, and Mr. Robert Nicholson; requests Franklin to favor them with his advice and good offices to forward their intended voyage.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 August 8; A.L.S. 1p.; John Gibson, Auditor-General. Philadelphia
    Informing them that the Treasury Board has made certain resolutions as regards the bills of exchange.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Tarteron, -----. Montpellier
    Addressed an ode to Franklin, some time in April, composed in honor of the insurgents; having received no answer, fears his letter miscarried.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Katz, Philipp Conrad. Bũdingen near Hanau on the Mayn
    Desires information concerning his brother, Georg Theobald Katz, who went to Philadelphia, in June, 1774, with his wife and three children. Has heard that his brother resided for a time with a wheelwright, Johannes Hrubacher, near Lancaster. Encloses letter to Brubacher and to his brother.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Bingham, William. St Pierre
    Repeats his announcement made in letter 25, concerning a bill drawn by him on the Commissioners.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Murphy, John. Boulogne
    Sailed from Rhode Island the 26th of August, 1777, in the sloop Swallow; had the misfortune to be taken and sent to Jamaica, thence in irons to England, where he made his escape from prison and arrived in Boulogne; begs for a line.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 10; A.L.S. 1 p.; de Champigny, Col Chevalier
    Fragment of a letter, concerning the payment of a subscription.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Leveux, Jacques. Calais
    Concerning two Americans who escaped from an English prison, and whose expenses to Paris he defrayed; one is Edward Leger, lieutenant on the Hornet, the other, Thomas Barnes, surgeon on the Hampden.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 11; D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[ratar]y. 1 p.; The Continental Congress
    Consigning the cargoes of several vessels to the American Commissioners at Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 12; A.L.S. 3p.; Parsons, ----- (William's wife). Paris
    Her astonishment that Franklin denied having given Mr. Parsons the least encouragement to go to America; protests against this view of the case. Details her miserable condition, alone in a foreign land, and in hourly expectation of being sent to prison for debts; begs Franklin to render her some assistance.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 August 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Moylan, James. L'Orient
    Containing an extract of a letter received from Lisbon, announcing the arrival there of the Albion, a seventy-four gun ship and one of Admiral Byron's squadron.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 12; A.L.S. 2p.; de Champigny, Col Chevalier. Amsterdam
    Asking for a certain sum still due on his subscription to the History of England; desires him also to subscribe to the History of Denmark or if he does not care to, to return the volumes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Guichard, —, ainé. Marennes
    Calling Franklin's attention once again to the affair of his brother, Augustin Guichard, to whom a certain sum of money is due for his service on board the Lexington.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 13; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Perronet, -----
    Sending a plan of the battle between the "English fleet and the King's army."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Peters, Richard. Philadelphia
    Begging Franklin to forward the enclosed important letter to his father; repeats his request to Franklin to supply his father with money. The recovery of Rhode Island and the capture of the British troops there daily expected. General Clinton besieged in New York by General Washington; the former's misfortune at Monmouth has taught him not to be adventurous.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 14; A.L.S. 4p.; de Reuschenberg, Baron F.E. Paris
    Lays before Franklin the advantages of the legion as a military formation and the extreme usefulness both on land and sea of amusettes, a small piece of artillery; ardently desires to fight for America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 14; A.L.S. 3p.; Hartley, David. London
    Exchange of prisoners. Remarks concerning peace, suggested by the report of the late negotiation between the Congress and the English Commissioners.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 295).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Clairbois, Vial du. Brest
    Begging Franklin to accept a copy of his book on naval architecture.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 August 15; A.L.S. 3p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. Brest
    Concerning a general report on the Ranger and through it to the French fleet, that he is turned out of the service and his place, with a captain's commissions given to Mr. Simpson, and that his letter of July 16th releasing Mr. Simpson from parole was forced from him; demands that he be afforded immediate redress by a court-martial. Compares his heart-whole devotion to America with the conduct of Simpson.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Cochran, Robert. Charlestown, S.C
    Acknowledging Franklin's kindness to his little son, whose behavior he trusts is such as to merit Franklin's approbation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 16; A.L.S. 3p.; Hutton, James. Zeist
    The passport for the vessel going to Labrador failed to arrive and the ship had to sail without it. Wishes to know it a French officer, M. Gaiault de Boisbertrand, got safely to France; he broke prison in England, having in vain attempted to procure an exchange. Desires passports for some of the Moravians who are going soon to Bethlehem. News of English friends.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 16; A.L.S. 3p.; Durand, -----. Paris
    Has just been appointed Consul for France in Sardinia. Applies for the Consulship of the United States at Barcelona for his father, Gabriel Durand, a resident of the latter city.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 19; L.S. 1p.; Hinman, E. Brest
    Arrived at Brest on the 17th and embarked on board the Providence, frigate, Captain Whipple; expects a speedy and safe passage.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 August 20; A.L.S. 3p.; Grand, Sir George. Amsterdam